<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the anniversary meeting of the gentlemen educated at St. Paul's School, at St. Paul's Church, January 25, 1698/9 by John Pulleyn ...</title>
            <author>Pulleyn, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56276</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34562</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14513449</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14513449</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102463</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56276)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102463)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1067:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the anniversary meeting of the gentlemen educated at St. Paul's School, at St. Paul's Church, January 25, 1698/9 by John Pulleyn ...</title>
                  <author>Pulleyn, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XX, 35 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:102463:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102463:1"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LLEYN</hi>'s SERMON Preach'd before the Gentlemen Educated at St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s SCHOOL, AT St. <hi>PAUL</hi>'s Church, <hi>Jan.</hi> 25. 1698/9.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102463:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102463:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at the Anniverſary Meeting OF THE Gentlemen Educated at <hi>St. Paul's School,</hi> AT St. <hi>PAUL</hi>'s Church, <hi>January</hi> 25. 1698/9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of the Stewards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN PULLEYN, A. M. And Prebendary of St. <hi>PAULS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102463:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102463:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE Worthy Gentlemen THE STEWARDS OF St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s School Feaſt:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Robert Fowle, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>John Killingworth, <abbr>
                        <hi>Esq</hi>
                     </abbr>
                  </item>
                  <item>George Smith, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Samuel Lloyd, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>John Baggs, <abbr>
                        <hi>Esq</hi>
                     </abbr>
                  </item>
                  <item>William Bonner, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THO' this Sermon was preached at your earneſt Requeſt, yet I could have wiſhed you would have excuſed me from the Publication of it. But ſince you would not be denyed, I ſhould be very well pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:102463:4"/>
if you ſhare not in the Faults and Imperfections of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> which you have now made your own, by eſpouſing the Subject, and obliging the Preacher to the Printing of it. I have only this to ſay for my ſelf, that your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norous inclinations <hi>to do Good,</hi> and your preſent Reſolutions to encourage all the Worthy Gentlemen, who were educated at St. <hi>PAUL's School,</hi> to lay a new Foundation of <hi>Charity</hi> for that <hi>Place,</hi> led me to the Subject of this enſuing Diſcourſe. And I hope this will be one Conſequent of it, that this beginning of your <hi>Charity</hi> will annually be emproved by all thoſe who bear any Relation or Love to the Place of their Education. And I do not queſtion, but ſucceeding Years may raiſe a noble Superſtructure of Charity from this Ground-work you have ſo happily
<pb facs="tcp:102463:4"/>
laid, for the Honour of our School, and for the Encouragement of all Arts and Learning.</p>
            <p>May all your excellent Deſigns proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, your Chriſtian Charity in General flouriſh, may you bring Honour to our Eſtabliſh'd Church and Kingdom, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you are Worthy Members, and may you never want a Bleſſing and Succeſs in all your particular Stations and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polyments; which is the hearty Wiſh of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Sincere and Humble Servant,</hi> John Pulleyn.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:102463:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102463:5"/>
            <head>ACTS XX. <hi>ver.</hi> 35. latter part.<hi>—It is more bleſſed to Give than to Receive.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>JOY and Pleaſure being the Bright ſide of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Life, it never touches the Heart and the Affections with a greater ſatisfaction, than when it ariſes from the Conſideration of thoſe many Bleſſings and Advantages, which reſult from Societies and Combinations of Men: And therefore it is not only a delightful Proſpect to me, but, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume likewiſe, to every one here preſent, to behold the Luſtre of this <hi>Solemn Day;</hi> the Deſign of which is ſo excellent and commendable, and all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of it ſo harmonious and beautiful. What can be more grateful and raviſhing, than to ſee the <hi>Children</hi> of one fruitful <hi>School,</hi> the Offspring of a Pious, Learned, and Religious <hi>Founder,</hi> to ſee them ſo well united to pay their ſincere Gratitude and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Place of their <hi>Education</hi> in the face of the World? And eſpecially to ſee them begin this their Gratitude with a dutiful acknowledgment to the great God of Heaven and Earth, in whom all that is now expected and deſired of us <hi>This Day</hi> ought to terminate? <hi>I was glad</hi> (ſaid the Royal Prophet) <hi>when</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 122. 1.</note> 
               <hi>they ſaid unto me, Let us go into the houſe of the Lord;</hi> glad to ſee, that <hi>thither the Tribes go up to give thanks unto the Name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>(Worthy School-Fellows,</hi> by whatever <hi>Titles</hi> you may be <hi>dignified</hi> above, or <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> from one another) ſince you have met together on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102463:6"/>
this Day, (and in this moſt <hi>Holy Place)</hi> which the Church hath ſet apart to commemorate the great Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to render Thanks for that Bleſſing of our <hi>Education</hi> in that <hi>School,</hi> which ſo worthily bears that <hi>Name,</hi> and which ought likewiſe ever to put us in mind of thoſe Benefits and Advantages we have received from thence, I hope this Religious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of our appearance this Day, will give a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and a ſucceſsful Influence upon the following part of your <hi>Solemnity,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing you are reſolved to retrieve in ſome meaſure the primitive <hi>Feaſt</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> which is in truth the chief and moſt laudable Deſign of theſe and other the like <hi>Anniverſary Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> A Deſign ſo noble and generous in it ſelf, ſo beneficial to others, ſo becoming Men, and ſo truly Chriſtian, that as it formerly obtained amongſt us, and met with good Encouragement, ſo I hope upon the revival of this Feaſt, it will now be carried on, and cheriſhed and ſupported both by the Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Contributions of all pious and well-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons.</p>
            <p>And therefore in regard all the Benefits and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of a Free and an Ingenuous <hi>Education,</hi> was the laſt Year excellently and fully in this <hi>Place,</hi> and upon the <hi>ſame Occaſion,</hi> declar'd unto you, I ſhall wave that Argument of Diſcourſe, and at preſent only entertain you with what is as ſuitable and proper to all the Purpoſes of our <hi>preſent Meeting,</hi> as will appear from the Conſideration of theſe Words of our bleſſed Saviour, here cited by St. <hi>Paul,—It is more bleſſed to give, than to receive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Words of the Holy Jeſus are not recorded by any of the <hi>Evangeliſts;</hi> the Goſpel of St. <hi>John,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102463:6"/>
and probably that of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> being not written when St. <hi>Paul</hi> cited them. He muſt therefore either receive them as an <hi>Oral Tradition</hi> from the Apoſtles, or ſome firſt-hand Witneſſes, or elſe from him, who gave him the firſt Inſtruction of his Office, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated the Goſpel to him; which he declared, he did not <hi>receive it from Men, but was taught it by the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> But notwithſtanding the <hi>firſt conveyers</hi> of this remarkable Sentence are uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, yet the <hi>Author</hi> of them is unqueſtionable; the Apoſtle plainly affirming that they were ſpoken by our bleſſed Saviour:<hi>—Remember the Words of the Lord Jeſus, how he ſaid, It is more bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which Words are to be expounded according to the meaſure and limitation of other Proverbial Sentences in Scripture, not as if they would hold in that full latitude, which <hi>Grammar</hi> and the ſound of Words will allow. The Meaning only is, that the Nature of Things is uſually ſuch, that generally ſpeaking, <hi>It is more bleſſed to give than to receive; Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpeaking,</hi> I ſay, upon a due ballance of <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> and a ſuppoſal of right <hi>Qualifications.</hi> For otherwiſe, if He that diſpenſes his <hi>Charity,</hi> doth it out of a Principle of <hi>Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Vain-glory,</hi> to gain a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> or ſtrengthen a Faction; If he do it to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach upon the juſt <hi>Liberties</hi> of the Perſon obliged, to upbraid him with his <hi>Neceſſities,</hi> to betray him into <hi>ſinful Compliances,</hi> and to make him abſolutely obnoxious to his <hi>Humour</hi> and <hi>Inclination,</hi> (a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Acknowledger and benevolent Receiver is much to be preferred before ſuch a Donor as this) ſuch ſcandalous Reſerves as theſe, are enough to take off the Value, and null the Obligation of the largeſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102463:7"/>
proportion of Alms and Liberality. If a Man ſhould give away a Kingdom upon ſuch narrow and vicious Conſiderations, none were obliged to thank him for it: Becauſe his Good-will did not accompany his Gift: becauſe he did not deſign his Neighbours Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, but his own: His only Motive was Vanity, Self-deſign, or Ill-nature. So that what he parts withal, is properly but Merchandiſe and Strategem; and conſequently tho' he gives all his Goods to the Poor, in the account of God and Reaſon, he is <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> he will never be the better for it, tho' others may. But then if we conſider the General Event of Things, if we ſuppoſe the <hi>Giver</hi> and the <hi>Receiver</hi> (purely conſidered as ſuch) to be free both from ill Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Moral Indiſpoſitions, we ſhall find the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage on the <hi>Givers</hi> ſide: which will appear, if we conſider the Meaning of the Text more diſtinctly.<hi>—It is more bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which Words may import theſe two Things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. That the Condition of the Giver is more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable than that of the Receiver, becauſe it is more ſatisfactory and ſecure, and ſo argues greater Perfection.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That <hi>Giving</hi> is more commendable than <hi>Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> becauſe generally ſpeaking, it is a clearer evidence of a noble and virtuous diſpoſition of Mind.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſay the Condition of the <hi>Giver</hi> is more deſirable than that of the <hi>Receiver,</hi> becauſe it includes greater Perfection; and that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> As it is a ſign of Sufficiency and Power.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102463:7"/>
Men generally underſtand, that the Law of Self-preſervation, allows them to furniſh themſelves with ſomething more, than the bare Neceſſities of Life, before they are obliged to aſſiſt their Neighbours; that tho' they be bound to <hi>love</hi> others as well as themſelves, yet not better: Nay they think, that if their Abilities are not large enough to divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their Neighbours Neceſſities and their own, in moſt Caſes they may lawfully prefer themſelves: And without queſtion, if Men ſtated the Caſe fairly, and account nothing Neceſſary, but what is really ſo, they might be allowed to practiſe by this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Now, according to this general Apprehenſion, He that gives to another, ſeems to be well provided for himſelf; he is ſuppoſed able to defray the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Charge of Life, and anſwer the juſt Importunities of Nature; and not only ſo, but to have a redundancy and ſuperfluity of Power to beſtow, where he judges convenient. He that <hi>Gives</hi> not only looks like a <hi>Full Being,</hi> whoſe Abilities are not wholly exhauſted upon it ſelf, but like a ſwelling River, which after it hath filled the Channel of its own deſires, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flows its Banks to relieve the barrenneſs of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Ground. Whereas <hi>Receiving</hi> implies Want and Weakneſs, empty Spaces, and unſatisfied Deſires, which a Man can't furniſh and content himſelf with, but muſt depend upon the arbitrary aſſiſtance of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The <hi>Giver</hi> reſembles a Fruitful Country, which hath all the conveniences of Life within it ſelf, and ſubſiſts upon the Product of its own Growth: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he that <hi>Receives,</hi> muſt undergo the labour and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of a long Voyage, and the uneaſineſs of a Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Commerce and Converſation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102463:8"/>
Beſides, <hi>Giving</hi> includes <hi>Choice;</hi> for what a Man parts with to another, he hath freedom to retain himſelf, and conſequenly he hath the power to aſſign the proportion of his own Liberalities, and may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve as much as he pleaſes for his own occaſions. And if he takes his <hi>Meaſures</hi> too narrow, he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to none but God Almighty. But the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver</hi> is not to be his own <hi>Carver;</hi> he can neither warrant the Certainty, or the Proportion of a Supply, but muſt depend in the Circumſtances of his ſupport upon the kindneſs of his Neighbour. We ſee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Power</hi> and an approach to Self-ſufficiency is a very deſirable Companion to any Being. <hi>Power</hi> is the greateſt active Attribute of God Almighty, and which provides ſatisfaction for the reſt of his Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perfections. This is that which makes him the Terror of the Wicked, and the aſſured Hope and Refuge of the Righteous. It is his Almighty Arm which brings his juſt Decrees into effect, and makes all his Councels ſtand. By this he is prepared to govern and judge the World in Righteouſneſs; to repay Vengeance to his Adverſaries, and to ſave thoſe to the uttermoſt that come to him. Whereas <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> unaſſiſted by <hi>Power,</hi> are but vain Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and inſignificant Wiſhes. What doth a Fine and Judicious Contrivance ſignifie, if we are not able to bring it about? What are we the better for foreſeeing an Evil, if we cannot prevent it? To ſee Reaſon lie fetter'd in Impotency, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrying in all its worthy Deſigns; to reflect, that Foreſight and Conſideration, and Thought cannot divert thoſe Misfortunes it ſo clearly diſcovers, muſt needs be very afflicting to any rational Being, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102463:8"/>
turn its Perfection into Miſery. So <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> when not ſeconded by Ability, doth but make the Owner uneaſie, becauſe he ſees it impoſſible for him to effect that which he hath ſo great a mind to. To have ſtrong Affections and Compaſſions for another, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being able to give them thoſe Advantages we judge proper for them, or to deliver them from thoſe Preſſures, which we imagine they lie under, doth but make a Man unhappy in his good Nature, and to languiſh away his generous Being in kind Wiſhes, and in ineffectual Deſires.</p>
            <p>From all which it follows, that in regard the <hi>Giver</hi> is ſuppoſed to have odds of <hi>Power</hi> in his hands, upon this account his Condition is more deſirable than that of the <hi>Receiver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Condition of the <hi>Giver</hi> is more deſirable, becauſe the juſt Liberty and ingenuous Temper of the Mind is beſt ſecured in ſuch Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>I conſeſs that Rational Beings, much more Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ought to be ſo immovably Great, as not to be ſway'd by the Accidents of Life; ſo humble and reſigned to Providence, as not to raiſe or ſink their Spirits, according to the various ſucceſſes of Things below. Yet not withſtanding this, we may obſerve, that this World hath an unhappy Command over the greateſt part of Mankind, Mens Minds uſually reſembling the Nature and Complexion of their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Affairs. When Men believe their Circumſtances are well ſupported, this is apt to inſpire them with generous Thoughts, and raiſes them to a certain <hi>Grandeur</hi> of Spirit. It gives them a conſiding <hi>Aire,</hi> and a well-aſſured <hi>Deportment;</hi> and if they have but diſcretion to keep themſelves from running into the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102463:9"/>
Extreams of Pride and Inſolence, their Actions are remarkably graceful, by having a noble mixture of Freedom, and unconcernedneſs in them. Thoſe who think their Accommodations not much ſhort of their Deſires, and have a competent aſſurance of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in it, are uſually free in their Sentiments and ſteady in their Reſolutions. They need not be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by a foreign Fancy and Direction. And therefore when they are ſo happy, as to be under the conduct of good Principles, they are in a fair way to keep them: Whereas on the contrary, an Indigent Condition ſinks the Mind below its native dignity, and makes it anxious ad diffident of it ſelf. It produces ſervile Thoughts, ignoble Councels, and unſteady Reſolutions. They are not always allowed to ſpeak and act according to the Dictates of their own Reaſon, but have their Humour and Practice preſcribed by others. For being unable to ſupport themſelves, and ſometimes the <hi>favour</hi> of thoſe, who are able to aſſiſt, is not to be gained without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to unwarrantable Complyances; They muſt, if they will ſucceed, diſſemble and flatter, and take no notice of the Imperfections, applaud ſometime, and imitate the Vices of their Benefactors, otherwiſe there is no countenance to be expected from them. In ſhort, they muſt be ſometimes contented to be ſlaves to the Pride and Folly of others, and to run thro' all the diſhonourable ways of Scandal and Meanneſs.</p>
            <p>Not but there hath been many Perſons of brave and excellent Spirits, whoſe <hi>Integrity</hi> is as remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as their <hi>Poverty;</hi> who have bore up againſt the moſt diſadvantageous Circumſtances, and ſcorn'd to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102463:9"/>
be over-awed into baſe and ſinful Obſequiouſneſs: who would not proſtitute their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and live upon the Spoils of their <hi>Honeſty.</hi> And as a Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitous Condition doth not force any to tranſgreſs their Duty to God, ſo neither doth it excuſe them, when they do: As it was their Choice, ſo it will be their Deſtruction, if they continue in it. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, thus much we may conclude, that Indigence and Poverty is more likely to produce abjectneſs of Mind, and is a greater temptation to ſinful Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and conſequently the Condition of the <hi>Receiver,</hi> is not ſo ſecure and deſirable as that of the <hi>Giver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Condition of the <hi>Giver</hi> implies an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Truſt committed to him by God Almighty.</p>
            <p>God, who is the ſupreme <hi>Proprietor,</hi> hath permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an unequal diſtribution of the Good Things of this Life, both for the better ſecurity of Government, and likewiſe to prove the Reſignation of the Poor, and the Juſtice and Humanity of the Wealthy. Now thoſe who have the greater ſhare of the diviſion fallen to them, have the honour to be God's <hi>Stewards</hi> and <hi>Almoners</hi> to diſpence the bleſſings of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to the <hi>Needy,</hi> and, as it were, in a literal ſenſe, to give his <hi>Houſhold</hi> their <hi>meat in due ſeaſon.</hi> The <hi>Poor</hi> are, as it were, <hi>Minors</hi> all their Life-time; they do not come to their Eſtate till the other World; and God therefore hath aſſigned the <hi>Rich</hi> for their <hi>Guardians,</hi> who are to ſupply their Neceſſities, and protect them from Injury and Oppreſſion. An ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Employment this is, by which the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſubſiſtance of our poor Brethren is entruſted with us, and their Lives are in a manner committed to us. It looks like a <hi>Teſtimonial</hi> of our Worth from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102463:10"/>
God Almighty, as if he had owned our <hi>Sufficiency</hi> for the diſcharge of this Office, and did not ſuſpect our Integrity in the management of it. We ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member therefore, as the Truſt is honourable and weighty, we are bound to perform it with a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable Care and Fidelity; and that St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath told us, <hi>that it is required in a Steward to be faithful.</hi> We ſhould conſider, that God never gives any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon any full and unconditional propriety in his Eſtate, but always reſerves a <hi>Rent-Charge</hi> out of it for the Uſe of the Poor, only the Summ is left to the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Owner; which, as it ought to be fairly and liberally ſtated, ſo we ſhould take care to pay it where it was due: neither throwing away our Lord's Money for the ſupport of Sloth and Lewdneſs, nor over-looking any deſerving Object. For as we ought not to be careleſs, ſo neither ſhould we be too ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous. For thoſe who won't afford their Charity without a demonſtration of real and compaſſionable Want, ſeem to love their Money much better than their Neighbour; and give a ſhrewd ſuſpition that they are willing to find a colourable Evaſion to lay aſide their <hi>Truſt,</hi> tho' their indigent Brother ſuffers never ſo much by it. But when (where we ſee apparent ſigns of Neceſſity lie before us) we have been as cautious, as the Circumſtances of the Occaſion will permit, we ſhould content our ſelves with a fair probability, and not ſtand upon a nice and curious enquiry into the Deſert of the Perſon. To this, both Duty to God, and good Nature to Man inclines us, conſidering that we cannot loſe by ſuch a Miſtake. For if the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon happens to be Unworthy, he doth not cheat us, but himſelf. If we are but prudentially careful, our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102463:10"/>
               <hi>Charity</hi> which was done out of Principles of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God and compaſſion to our Neighbour, will never fare the worſe for the wickedneſs and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie of the <hi>Receiver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Meaning of the Words of the <hi>Text,</hi> and which we have reaſon to believe our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> chiefly intends, is, that <hi>Giving</hi> is more commendable than <hi>Receiving,</hi> becauſe <hi>generally ſpeaking,</hi> it is a clearer evidence of a Noble and Vertuous diſpoſition of Mind: And that on theſe four Accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is a greater ſign of Goodneſs. I know it may be objected, that the <hi>Receiver</hi> may plead a Title to this Quality, as well as the other. For it is a fault not to <hi>receive,</hi> as well as not to <hi>give.</hi> To refuſe an Obligation (except where we have reaſon to ſuſpect that the Deſign and the Event may be ill, that it comes from a bad Intention, and brings ill Conſequences along with it) is a ſign of a haughty and unſociable Temper. To reject the Gift, either ſuppoſes it unſuitable to our Condition, or unſafe to accept, and conſequently reproaches him that offers it with indiſcretion or inſincerity. By refuſing his Kindneſs, we undervalue his Perſon and renounce his Friendſhip, plainly declaring, that we are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to enter into an amicable correſpondence and familiarity with him. It is an argument of Pride, of a ſhy and unconverſable Suſpitiouſneſs: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Rule of Contraries, to be willing to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> ſeems to argue an humble and humane diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Mind, that hath worthy and charitable Thoughts of Man, that thinks no Evil, but is ready upon all occaſions to enter into a ſtrict union and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe with others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102463:11"/>
But here we muſt conſider that this Objection is not valid, but where the Condition of the <hi>Receiver</hi> is well ſupported; where he is able to provide for himſelf without the <hi>Benevolence</hi> of others. For if his Circumſtances are indigent, tho' his Temper be very humane, tho' his Inclination may be (and often is) very friendly and generous, yet the diſadvantage of his Condition hinders theſe commendable Qualities from ſhewing of themſelves. His Neceſſity is judged ſufficient to make him willing to come under an Obligation without the conjunction of any other more creditable <hi>Motives;</hi> which makes his <hi>Receiving</hi> look like a much greater argument of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to himſelf than others. But to <hi>give</hi> when there are no apparent marks of an ill Intention, is a fair indication of a rich and of a benevolent diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is a generous exerciſe of <hi>Power.</hi> It ſhews that we wiſh Mankind happy, by our endeavouring to make them ſo. What can be a more convincing Proof of the tender and compaſſionate ſenſe we have of the Wants and Afflictions of others, than to be willing to part with ſome Conveniencies of our own to receive them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Giving</hi> is a better evidence of a virtuous diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Mind, becauſe it is a ſign of a greater diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement from the World. <hi>Receiving</hi> may conſiſt well enough with covetous Deſires, with a narrow and anxious Mind, with a diſtruſt of Providence, and an over-valuing Opinion of the Things of this Life. He that <hi>receives,</hi> I ſay, may have all theſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble Qualities. I do not mean that he hath them, but that there is nothing to the contrary implied in the Act of <hi>Receiving:</hi> But now on the other ſide,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102463:11"/>
to part with our Wealth freely towards the promoting of worthy and charitable Deſigns, is a good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a great and a religious Mind, that hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable thoughts of Providence, and relies upon it, and is ſecure and unconcern'd about the Events of this Life; ſuch a Perſon ſeems to underſtand the true Uſe of this World, and to have no more than a juſt value for it. He will not be governed and enſlaved by his Fortune, but is reſolved to make uſe of it for thoſe Purpoſes God gave it him, and rather chooſes to live Charitably than die Rich. He that <hi>forgets not to do good and to communicate,</hi> gives us good aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that his Converſation is in Heaven; that he hath made a higher choice, and is in perſuit of nobler Objects, than are to be met with here. For if he aimed at nothing but this World, we have reaſon to believe he would never ſo freely part with it. But when the Abilities of the <hi>Giver</hi> are ſmall, when he hath nothing but his Labour and Induſtry to depend upon for the future; when as St. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> Men are willing to <hi>give</hi> not only <hi>according</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 3.</note> 
               <hi>to, but beyond their Power,</hi> and like the Widow in the Goſpel, caſts, as it were, their whole Living into the Poors Treaſury; This is an undeniable evidence both of the generouſneſs and devotion of their Spirits, that they have worthy apprehenſions of God, and are benevolently inclined toward their Neighbours.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſing the <hi>Giver</hi> and the <hi>Receiver</hi> both rightly diſpoſed, yet the due Qualifications of the firſt will contribute more to the happineſs of the other World, than thoſe of the latter: <hi>i. e.</hi> Charity will promote our future Happineſs more than bare Gratitude.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102463:12"/>
Our bleſſed Saviour, where he tells us that <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> thoſe of his right hand ſhall be called to <hi>inherit the Kingdom prepared for them,</hi> gives us the reaſon of this Invitation, <hi>viz.</hi> That becauſe they had been Charitable and Beneficent, fed the Hungry, cloath'd the Naked, and adminiſtred comfort and relief to thoſe who were in Diſtreſs. He doth not ſay, you have been grateful toward your Benefactors, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred their good Deeds, and pray'd for them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come <hi>into the Kingdom prepared for you.</hi> Tho' theſe are undoubtedly Virtues, yet the rewarding Sentence is not founded upon theſe: Neither ſhall we wonder to find <hi>Charity</hi> preferred before Gratitude, if we conſider, that according to the general Temper of Mankind, the exerciſe of it, hath more of difficulty in it, and the Effects of it are more beneficial. A Man may be <hi>grateful</hi> without being at the expence of any thing, but a little Pride. He loſes nothing but a ſtubborn Humour, which is uſually ſo far morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by ſtrait Circumſtances, that People can part with it, without much trouble. The acknowledging of a Kindneſs is ſo far from diminiſhing any Man's Fortune, that it rather gives him a proſpect of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing it. But he that <hi>gives</hi> in any conſiderable meaſure parts with a real Advantage, and is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at leaſt ſo much the Poorer by it. Now in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the good Things of this Life are in our actual poſſeſſion, and likewiſe agreeable to our inclination, Men find ſome difficulty to part with them, unleſs they have a ſtrong ſenſe of Duty upon them, and their hearts are enlarged by Religious Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Beſides, to be <hi>Charitable,</hi> is much more neceſſary to the ſupport of Mankind, than to be <hi>Grateful.</hi> For
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102463:12"/>
Gratitude is uſually due to the wealthy and powerful, who are able to provide for themſelves, tho' their Favours ſhould happen to be unacknowledged: but Charity reſpects the poor and needy, who abſolutely depend upon its aſſiſtance. <hi>Ingratitude</hi> often only diſappoints and diſquiets, but Uncharitableneſs brings real Miſchiefs along with it. A man looſes nothing but his Expectation by the one, but his Life may be in danger by the other.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Gratitude</hi> ſeems to be commanded upon the accounts of <hi>Charity,</hi> and therefore muſt be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to it. To be Grateful is a Virtue, chiefly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch a diſpoſition encourages thoſe, who have power, to aſſiſt their Neighbours. For Men are not generally arrived to ſuch a diſintereſted pitch of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as to give purely out of Principles of Humanity: Nay, tho' they believe they ſhall be mightily rewarded for what they do, yet they are not willing to ſtay for the whole return of their <hi>Charity</hi> till the other World. If they have not ſome preſent payment in <hi>Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Acknowledgment,</hi> they are apt to be diſcouraged, and grow weary of well-doing. But a juſt Senſe of their Favours ſupports their charitable Diſpoſition, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites it to proceed. A grateful return, convinces them, that they were not miſtaken in their Object, and conſequently confirms them in the Diſcretion of their choice, and is moreover an acknowledgement of their Goodneſs and Power. Now ſuch Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as theſe Men are willing others ſhould have of them. Since therefore Gratitude is chiefly enjoin'd to promote Charity, it muſt be own'd to be of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Order, and conſequently, as the Virtue of the <hi>Giver</hi> hath a fairer Trial than that of the <hi>Receiver,</hi> ſo likewiſe it is of a higher Order.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:102463:13"/>
4. Another Reaſon, Why <hi>it is more bleſſed, &amp;c.</hi> is, becauſe there is more pleaſure in it, and that upon Three Accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it makes us inſtrumental in promoting the Good of others. The Charitable Perſon (where his Fortune bears any tolerable proportion with the largeneſs of his Mind) is the great and univerſal Remedy againſt the Calamities and Misfortunes of Life. He is as it were, a Father to the Fatherleſs, Eyes to the Blind, and Feet to the Lame. He is Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to the Captive, and if not Health, yet Eaſe and Refreſhment to the Sick: Now to be able in ſome meaſure to remove Want and Pain, and Diſeaſes out of the World, to make the minds of the Needy more chearful, and their Bodies more acceptable and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to them; to do this, I ſay, muſt be no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſatisfaction to a well-diſpoſed Mind. What a ſtrange alteration do we ſee in a <hi>poor man,</hi> when he receives a liberal Alms at the hand, or a Refreſhment at the Table of another? All Senſe of his former Wants ſeem to be forgotten, and his Soul, his Looks, and Motion, ſeem to be animated with Joy, and have the very meen and image of Contentment in them. He ſeems to be made over again, and to have freſh Ingredients of Happineſs thrown into his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. It's not unuſual to ſee ſuch a Perſon more tranſported with the receiving a <hi>few pence,</hi> than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is with the news of an <hi>Eſtate.</hi> And muſt it not be very entertaining, to abate, if not to extinguiſh the Miſery of one of our own Nature, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate Pleaſure at ſo cheap a rate? One would think, a Man could not lay out his Money ſo much to his ſatisfaction any other way. It muſt needs be a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102463:13"/>
mighty Pleaſure to a good Man to be in a Capacity of making others happy. For by this he hath an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of gratifying his generous inclinations, and of effecting that which he ſo much deſires. By putting others into a good condition he ſecures and improves his own. For by making eaſie and leſſening the Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences of Mankind, he ſo far prevents the interruption of his own Happineſs, which would otherwiſe ariſe from Pity and Compaſſion. The kind affection he hath for his Neighbour, makes him <hi>rejoice with them that rejoice,</hi> and counts anothers happineſs his own. To do Good is very delightful, becauſe by this we are aſſured, that our Mind is benign and humane, that it is in its right conſtitution; that Covetouſneſs, Malice, and Envy, do not bear rule within us, but that we are free from the ſhame and diſturbance of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſie and ſcandalous Paſſions. By this we are conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous that we are of the ſame temper with God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; which as it is the greateſt honour we are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, ſo if we are like him, we are ſure we muſt be acceptable to him, and that he will publickly own his approbation of us afterwards to our unſpeakable reward.</p>
            <p>To which we may add, that the Matter of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefaction often continues but a little while. An Alms may be ſoon ſpent and gone, and the <hi>Receiver</hi> in diſtreſs for want of another; but the advantage of him that <hi>gave</hi> it is not of ſo frail and ſhort-liv'd a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The pleaſure of a Charitable action keeps us company all along in this World, and in the next too. It is turned as it were into the ſubſtance of the Soul, and is as immortal as the Will from whence it came. It hath a happy influence upon all ſorts of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102463:14"/>
Accidents and Conditions. It doubles our Proſperity, and ſupports our Adverſity; it makes us enjoy our Life, and be leſs ſurpriſed at the approaches of Death. Indeed the Pleaſure with which the Charitable Man is entertained with here, and the Rewards which are promiſed to him afterward, is ſo great, that we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly <hi>miſunderſtand</hi> and <hi>miſcall</hi> things. For proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaking, the <hi>Receivers</hi> are the <hi>Benefactors.</hi> The greateſt Obligation comes from the Needy, becauſe they are the occaſion of a far greater advantage to their Neighbour, than what they receive from him; ſo that when the Gain is computed on both ſides, the <hi>Receiver</hi> looks moſt like the Charitable Perſon. From whence it will follow, that the Poor ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be courted and importuned, than denied, and we ſhould be more forward to offer them our aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance than they are to ask it.</p>
            <p>To this it may be replied, that theſe Advantages do not come from the <hi>Receiver,</hi> nor depend upon him; tho, if he is a good Man, his Prayers are no mean Requital. The great advantages of <hi>Charity</hi> proceed chiefly from God's goodneſs, who is pleaſed to entail ſo great a reward upon it; and partly from the generous Mind of the <hi>Giver,</hi> who delights in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, and in aſſiſting of others: and therefore next to God, he is the <hi>Author</hi> of his own Pleaſure, which doth not depend upon the <hi>Will,</hi> or <hi>Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of him he relieves, but ſprings from that noble diſpoſition of his own Mind. However the Objection hath truth enough in it to excite us to Charity, and to make us cheriſh the Poor for our own ſake, as well as theirs, who, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, are the happy occaſions <hi>of making many rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:102463:14"/>
2. There is more pleaſure in <hi>Giving,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe from hence, we have the ſatisfaction to believe that others have worthy apprehenſions of us.</p>
            <p>As Men generally think well of themſelves, ſo they are deſirous others ſhould do ſo too. For beſides the advantages they may expect from ſuch a ſenſe of the concurring judgment of their Neighbours; it confirms them in the good Opinion they have of themſelves, which is by no means unacceptable to them. Reputation is a thing ſo much coveted, that Men are willing to expoſe themſelves to the greateſt hazards to purchaſe it: Nay ſo <hi>fantaſtically</hi> fond are ſome Perſons of the acknowledgment of their good qualities, that they are willing to have a <hi>ſtock</hi> of <hi>Fame</hi> going after they are dead: never conſidering that it ſignifies nothing, tho' the whole World rings in a Man's applauſe, if in the mean time he hears and knows nothing of it. But notwithſtanding our affecting good Opinion of others is not unlawful, when it is void of Pride, Ambition and Vanity; when it is only deſired to encourage us in Vertue, and to give us the fairer opportunities of doing good to our Neighbour.</p>
            <p>Now by <hi>Receiving</hi> a Man can't ſo certainly col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, that he ſtands in the good opinion of others. For Men are often ſo cenſorious, as to conclude, that his Neceſſity was occaſioned by his Neglect, or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality; and that it was not his Merit, but his Want, which moved the religious compaſſion of the <hi>Giver</hi> to aſſiſt him. But he that is <hi>liberal</hi> and <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> in any Remarkable Degree, hath uſually a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſtruction put upon his Actions. The <hi>Envious</hi> are almoſt afraid to detract from his Merits, and he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102463:15"/>
may fairly preſume, that he is approved by the <hi>Generality,</hi> and entertain himſelf with the ſatisfaction of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another advantage of <hi>Giving</hi> is this, that it will enlarge the Generality of our Minds, and make us more diſpoſed to proſecute the Good of others.</p>
            <p>The exerciſe of this Virtue will not only, like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther habits, grow eaſie by Cuſtom, but readily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engage us from narrow and tenacious Principles. And there is a particular reaſon, why we ſhould improve under the practice of it. For it is natural for Men to love thoſe they have obliged. They look upon ſuch Perſons as <hi>Creatures</hi> of their own making; and therefore they love to purſue and ſecond one Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with another. Should they ceaſe to oblige, this would (they know) reflect upon the Diſcretion of their firſt choice. They might fear, that what they have beſtowed already would be in a great meaſure loſt, and that others would ſuſpect, that the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Mind began to decay, and to contract it ſelf into its own private Intereſt. Love is obſerved to deſcend more vigorouſly from the Parent to the Child, than to move the other way. The reaſon is probably, becauſe they look upon them as being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from themſelves, and grow up into ſtrength and maturity under their care and protection: which makes them cheriſh and rejoice in the Effects of their own Power, and Kindneſs, and imagine themſelves to flouriſh in their Offspring. Now the <hi>Receiver,</hi> if he is not of a very happy and Chriſtian Temper, if the Obligation was not conferr'd upon him with frankneſs and affability, he will not find himſelf in any vigorous diſpoſition toward <hi>Gratitude.</hi> For there
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102463:15"/>
is nothing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> more certain, than that the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mens inability and dependance, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults from the Relation of a <hi>Benefactor,</hi> make ſome Perſons abate in their affections toward him. But the <hi>obliging Perſon</hi> hath a delightful ſenſe and proſpect of his Condition. He views himſelf under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> which is a ſtrong Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to invite his Charity and Beneficence, becauſe he finds himſelf magnified by it, and the farther advances he makes in the exerciſe of this Vertue, the more he raiſes the Elevation of his Being.</p>
            <p>Thus, I hope, I have, in ſome meaſure, made good the Truth of theſe excellent Words of our Saviour,<hi>—It is more bleſſed to give than to receive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall briefly infer ſomething from the Text, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Since it is more <hi>happy to Give than to Receive,</hi> I think we ought carefully to avoid all <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>ſuperfluouſneſs</hi> in the managery of our Fortunes, that ſo we may be the better able to contribute more liberally to thoſe that want. Indeed were there no ſuch thing as Want and Neceſſity in the World, was every one competently furniſhed with the Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies of Life, Men might then have been permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a freer, and a more indulgent uſe of their Wealth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then, provided that they had not fallen into any vicious Exceſſes, they might have been allowed to entertain their Appetites at a more expenſive rate, and to have pleaſed their little <hi>Fancies</hi> with the <hi>glitterings</hi> of State and Magniſicence. For tho' a ſtrong propenſity to the pleaſures of Senſe, and an affected oſtentation of Riches would be an argument of a weak and an obnoxious Mind, yet <hi>others</hi> would
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102463:16"/>
not have been the worſe for ſuch an Extravagance. But now ſince we have the <hi>Poor</hi> always with us, ſince there are ſo many in indigent and unſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Circumſtances, if we prefer the <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacy</hi> of an unaccountable <hi>Deſire,</hi> before the <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities</hi> of our <hi>Brethren,</hi> we are both <hi>Unjuſt</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>human.</hi> For what can be more unaccountable, than to throw away the ſurpluſage of our Fortune upon empty and inſignificant <hi>Shews,</hi> when there are ſo many Misfortunes and Miſeries of Mankind, which might have been in a great meaſure removed and alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated by us. And as there is nothing more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and unrighteous to ſpend the <hi>Patrimony</hi> of the <hi>Poor</hi> upon Luxury and Pride; ſo it likewiſe deprives us of the great <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> which is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to a Charitable diſpoſition. Such a Perſon can't conclude that he hath the Favour and Eſteem either of God or Man: the belief of which is one of the greateſt ſupports and entertainments to a rational Mind. On the contrary, if he hath but ſenſe and impartiality enough to examine his own Actions and Temper, when he ſees how ſelfiſh and narrow-ſpirited he is, how void of the proper Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and Generoſity of his kind, in this Caſe, if he have any apprehenſion of Good and Evil left him, he cannot chooſe, but be a very unagreeable Spectacle to himſelf, and condemn himſelf in thoſe Things which he allows.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe which are <hi>Receivers</hi> ought not to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur againſt the Providence of God, and be diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with their <hi>Condition.</hi> That the <hi>Givers</hi> Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances are more deſirable, muſt be granted for the forementioned Reaſons. But to draw the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:102463:16"/>
ſomewhat towards an evenneſs, we may add, that as the <hi>Receiver's Condition</hi> is not ſo liable to ſome <hi>Vices,</hi> as the other is, ſo neither hath he ſo large an <hi>Account</hi> to give up afterwards. For as our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> tells us, that <hi>to whom much is given, much will be required,</hi> ſo he whoſe <hi>Truſt</hi> is ſmall, will have the leſs proportion of Stock and Improvement to be anſwerable for. Beſides, by his Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and good Wiſhes, and Prayers, he hath a fair opportunity of diſcharging the <hi>Debt,</hi> and returning the Obligation upon the moſt <hi>Conſiderable Benefactor.</hi> As for <hi>Dependance,</hi> which all Mankind have a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural averſion to, is rather out of a Spirit of native Greatneſs than Pride: I ſay, this unacceptable <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance</hi> of a <hi>Low Condition,</hi> is not ſo peculiar to it, as to be the <hi>Poor-man's</hi> Fate alone. This is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience that purſues the <hi>Indigent</hi> and <hi>defenceleſs</hi> State of humane Nature in general: there being no rank nor degrees of Men, raiſed to that height of <hi>Self-ſufficiency,</hi> but are in ſome meaſure ſenſible of the weight and uneaſineſs of it.</p>
            <p>As long as Men carry theſe frail Bodies about them; they muſt lie at the mercy of a <hi>foreign Aſſiſtance,</hi> and be ſubject ſometimes to the <hi>Inſolence</hi> and <hi>Ill-nature</hi> of an uncompaſſionate and haughty Diſpoſition. But when we have nothing but a <hi>poor Spirit</hi> to take care of, which is able to maintain it ſelf upon the ſtrength of its own Being, it is impregnable againſt all Aſſault: And when this <hi>Mortal</hi> ſhall have put on Immortality, and ſhall be no longer liable to Want, or expoſed to Injury, then all the Cauſes of <hi>Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> will vaniſh and fall off, and Men in the moſt comprehenſive ſenſe, will be tranſlated into the moſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102463:17"/>
               <hi>glorious Liberty of the Sons of God.</hi> For notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>Saints</hi> will have different degrees of Glory, proportionable to the great Works of Piety and Goodneſs they have done here, yet this <hi>Diſtinction</hi> will not ſubject thoſe of the <hi>Loweſt Order,</hi> to any <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance</hi> upon a Superior Quality. For the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us then, that <hi>all Rule and Authority ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> 
               <hi>be put down, and God ſhall be all in all.</hi> Which noble State of <hi>Freedom</hi> muſt, without all queſtion, much endear the Society of that Place, and conſequently augment the happineſs of thoſe, who have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to make a part of it.</p>
            <p>3. And Laſtly, Since the Caſe ſtands thus with us, I ſhall in a very few words more, exhort every one here preſent to this Duty of Charity: I <hi>mean,</hi> more particularly, <hi>thoſe of us,</hi> who have enjoyed the advantages of a <hi>Liberal Education</hi> at <hi>St. Paul's School.</hi> And if ever I could hope to prevail and perſuade in this Matter, I ſhould certainly expect no little Succeſs in ſuch an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> as this, which conſiſts of <hi>Perſons</hi> well Taught and Bred, whoſe Natures have been refined and poliſhed, and whoſe Minds have been improved and cultivated, new moulded and faſhioned by the Care and Skill of thoſe <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perſons,</hi> to whoſe Charge we were committed.</p>
            <p>The ſeveral Meetings and Solemn Feaſts, which the <hi>Jews</hi> (who were a Particular Society and Body of Men diſtinct from the reſt of the World) held unto the Lord, were appointed and inſtituted by God himſelf; ſuch were the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> the Feaſt of <hi>Harveſt,</hi> and <hi>Ingathering:</hi> And there was very great care taken in the ſtrict Obſervation of them, that none were then to <hi>appear Empty before the Lord.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:102463:17"/>
And tho' this <hi>Feſtival Aſſembly,</hi> this <hi>Anniverſary Feaſt</hi> which we <hi>hold now unto the Lord,</hi> hath not the ſame Divine Authority to warrant its Inſtitution, yet I am ſure it hath the ſame pious and laudable Ends accompanying it. For we are here met in this <hi>Sacred Place</hi> to offer up our Praiſes and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings for all thoſe excellent Advantages, which we by his goodneſs have obtained from a Free and an Ingenuous Education at our <hi>School.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>To praiſe him with our Mouths, whoſe Lips he hath opened with the Key of Knowledge, to rejoice before him, that our Lot fell to us in ſo good a Ground. That</hi> he vouchſafed <hi>to plant us by the Water-Springs, by the Rivulets of Knowledge, that we might bring forth the ſeveral Fruits of our proper Callings in our due time and ſeaſon.</hi> Neither in this our Meeting muſt <hi>we appear before the Lord Empty;</hi> ſeeing that our Charity and our Piety ought to go hand in hand, and kiſs each other.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then ſhew our Tenderneſs of Thought and Affection to the Place, where we received our Inſtitution, and had our younger Years ſeaſoned with Honeſt and Religious Principles, and laid a ſolid Foundation for our after-life to live upon. Let this Love be expreſſed by a liberal Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it; I mean, for the Educating of <hi>good Mens poor Children,</hi> in uſeful Literature and Knowledge: This being one of the moſt beneficial Acts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we owe to it: To take a Youth, that is poor and deſtitute of all advantages of Education, and to bring him up in the knowledge and fear of God, and to put him into a way, wherein by his future diligence and induſtry he may arrive to an honeſt Livelihood in this World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:102463:18"/>
Let us depoſite this Tribute of our Affection for this Uſe, and what you leave with the <hi>Worthy Stewards</hi> of the Eeaſt this Day, be an Earneſt-peny of your Generous Inclinations in doing ſomething further, as God ſhall bleſs you, for the advantage of our <hi>School</hi> in ſucceeding Years to come. Reſolve to do this before you go hence, <hi>before the Lord your God, from the Ground of your Heart,</hi> and make him ſome chearful and ſuitable acknowledgment of his diſtinguiſhing Providence towards you and yours. So ſhall the reſt of your Subſtance be bleſſed and increaſed, the Honour of our <hi>School</hi> promoted and advanced, ſo as that Generations to come will riſe up at the mentioning of your Names, and call you Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>In a word. Great will your Reward be that you will have <hi>in the Lord,</hi> ſince you are aſſured from the ſacred Writ, <hi>that God is not unrighteous to forget your Work and Labour of Love, which you have herein ſhewn towards his Name, in that you have Miniſtred unto them, and yet reſolve to Miniſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all Honour, Glory, Power, Might, Majeſty and Dominion, from this time forth, and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102463:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
